# **BEN SGHAIER OUSSAMA**

## PhD student at the University of Montreal

I am a PhD student at the University of Montreal. I work with Dr. Houari Sahraoui from GEODES lab. My research interests involve using AI techniques, specifically Deep Learning and Natural Language Processing, to automate/optimize software tasks and assist scientists/software engineers in their work.

Montreal, Canada

(438) 926-3336 oussama.ben.sghaier@iro.umontreal.ca

linkedin.com/in/oussamaben-sghaier/

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Research project: January 2021 -

GEODES Lab, (Supervised by: Dr. Houari Sahraoui), University of Montreal, QC, Canada

- · Intelligence artificielle (IA) en support des processus de développement logiciel: une
  - · Artificial Intelligence in support of software development processes: a work psychology perspective.
  - · Using Deep Learning models to automate the process of source code review.

#### Internship (Mitacs Accelerate Program): June 2020 - January 2021

Artificial Intelligence Department, National Bank of Canada, QC, Canada

- Automation and improvement of the software development pipeline:
  - · Identification of potential issues/improvements in the AI pipeline of the company.
  - o Build a cartography of Machine Learning-based opportunities.

#### September 2019 - January 2021 Research project:

GEODES Lab, (Supervised by: Dr. Houari Sahraoui), University of Montreal, QC, Canada

- · Towards using Artificial Intelligence techniques to assist software specialists in their tasks
  - · Quality-driven multi-objective optimization approach for metamodel refactoring.
  - · Metamodel refactoring using constraint solving.
  - · Cartography of AI-based opportunities to improve the Machine Learning pipeline.

#### Graduation Project: February 2019 - June 2019

Intelligent Software Engineering Laboratory, University of Michigan, MI, USA

- · Intelligent Refactorings Documentation
  - Recommending Refactorings via Commits Message Analysis.
  - · Semi-Automated Refactoring Documentation Bot.

Internship: Datarox, June 2018 - August 2018

Datarox company, Tunisia

LabSat Chatbot:get feedbacks from users and analyzing them with machine learning algorithms.

#### January 2018 - May 2018 Academic Deep Learning project,

National Institute of Applied Sciences and Technology, Tunisia

Automatic recognition of tags from questions.

Research project, January 2018 - May 2018

National Institute of Applied Sciences and Technology, Tunisia

· Big Data decision-making application respecting Big ETL architecture: Combining Business Intelligence and Big Data

Free-lance: October 2017 - May 2018

Efret company, Tunisia

· Mobile application for the "Efret" platform .

Internship: June - August 2017

Insight Scale company, Tunisia

· In-Memory Data Management Platform to support Real-Time promotions, advertising and up-sell of services.

Internship: June 2016 - September 2016

Intilaq company, Tunisia

· Development of a mobile app of Offers & Requests & Auctions

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD, Artificial Intelligence

2021 - , University of Montreal Montreal. Canada.

### Master dgree, Artificial Intelligence

2019 - current, University of Montreal, Montreal, Canada.

#### Master of Research, Information Processing and Complexity of the Living

2018 - 2019 ,National School of Engineers of Tunis (ENIT), Tunisia Co-degree with the Master's degree in Computer Science from Paris Descartes University, Paris, France

### Engineering degree, Software Engineering

2014-2019 National Institute of Applied Sciences and Technology, Tunisia

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

 Ben Sghaier, Oussama, Houari Sahraoui, Michalis Famelis "Metamodel Refactoring using Constraint Solving: a Quality-based Perspective." SAM 2021 - System Analysis and Modelling 2021

https://sdl-forum.org/Events/SAM2021/acceptedpapers.htm

- Ben Sghaier, Oussama, Houari Sahraoui, Eugène Syriani "Fighting evil is not enough when refactoring metamodels: Promoting the good also matters" The 36th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium On Applied Computing 2022 - SAC 2022 (under review)
- Rebai, Soumaya, Marouane Kessentini, Vahid Alizadeh, Oussama Ben Sghaier, and Rick Kazman.
  "Recommending refactorings via commit message analysis." Information and Software Technology 126 (2020): 106332.

https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0950584920300914

• Rebai, Soumaya, Oussama Ben Sghaier, Vahid Alizadeh, Marouane Kessentini, and Meriem Chater. "Interactive refactoring documentation bot." In 2019 19th International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation (SCAM), pp. 152-162. IEEE, 2019.

https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/8930873

### **TEACHING**

• Teaching assistant, Fall 2021

IFT 2255 - Software Engineering

http://www-ens.iro.umontreal.ca/~lafontle/ift2255

#### **VOLUNTEERING**

- Student Volunteer, MODELS, 2021.
- Student Volunteer, MODELS, 2020.

### **AWARDS & DISTINCTIONS**

- Tunisia National Scholarship, 2019.
- Qualified for the ACPC (Arab Collegiate Programming Contest) in Egypt.
- 5th place in the national TCPC (Problem Solving contest).
- 1st prize at SecuriLight
- 3rd place at hackaton "App For Democracy".
- 2nd place at the Android Coding Party

#### **LANGUAGES**

English, French, Arabic